JOTHI ARUL PRAKASH PONNUSAMI

Security Analyst

jothiarulprakash@gmail.com | 427, Creek Crossing RD NE, Vienna, VA, 22180 | +1(571)-327-7788 | https://www.linkedin.com/in/jothiarulprakash | jothiarulprakash.github.io

SUMMARY

Highly motivated Security Analyst experienced in detecting and securing information with a capability of troubleshooting and investigation of events and skilled in auditing the security controls to ensure policies are compliant with the security standards.

EDUCATION

George Mason University, Fairfax, Virginia

May 2020

Master's in Information Security and Assurance

Anna University, India Apr 2018

Bachelor's in Computer Science and Engineering

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Teaching Assistant, George Mason University

Aug 2019 - May 2020

- Handling online and in-class lecture sessions in security for high school students.
- Mentoring students by conducting hands-on activities dealing with security management.
- Developed basic system configuration and troubleshooting methods to identify the network and system connectivity issues with general assessment tasks.
- Mentoring students, evaluating assignments and awarding grades based on academic progress.

Operations Officer, Blockchain at Mason

Jan 2020 - May 2020

- Managing and analyzing projects of multiple domains.
- Participated in the 'Youth Engineering Conference 2020' to present fundamentals of blockchain.
- Organizing meetups with peer students to discuss upcoming events and connecting with blockchain professionals for research and development.
- Framed and proposed a fundamental blockchain curriculum for training students from different specialization.

Associate Software Engineer, Accenture, India

Apr 2018 - July 2018

- Developed and managed project on web-based employee portal application by permitting authenticated users to view authorized components by database interconnectivity.
- Tested the application functionalities like domain connectivity through a secure SSL/TLS connection, user authentication, and dynamic data storage in the database.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Programming : C, Java, Python, JavaScript, Shell Scripting.

Tools & Technology : IAM, Firewalls, IDS/IPS, AWS, SIEM- Splunk, Burp Suite, Eclipse, Wireshark, MySQL, VMWare,

Apache Tomcat, PKI, Microsoft Office, USB Forensics.

Standards & Frameworks: PCI-DSS, SOX-COBIT, RMF, NIST 800-53, ISO 27001.

PROJECTS AND RESEARCH

Application Development

- Secured storage of user information and geolocation data in Google Firebase Tourism App for Ministry of Tourism, India to facilitate tourists in India.
- Secured Cloud-based data sensing model to measure electricity consumption with real-time data and enhanced user alert notification system by using Google Firebase and Arduino platform.
- Secured multi-player web application game by implementing secure SSL/TLS connection, Password hashing, user session management, CSRF and XSS Protection to enhance the confidentiality and integrity of players and game availability.

Academic Research

- Blockchain implementation in IoT Devices for safe communication and avoid intrusion in the protected environment.
- Novel Intrusion Detection System implementation in a Drone network to detect real-time malicious traffic by notifying
 operational changes based on wavelet analysis and curve similarity score.
- Participated in MIT COVID-19: Beat the Pandemic Challenge- I & II to propose a decentralized news verification platform using Blockchain and County-based risk management application to prevent public by dynamic user risk assessment program.

Malware Analysis

• Static and Dynamic Analysis of WannaCry Ransomware with a simulation of propagation and key management using the cryptographic model and a real-time demonstration.